Carnegie Mellon University Women's Center Records 1988-1994
Carnegie Mellon University
1988-1994
3/4 linear feet [1 Box]
University Archives
Carnegie-Mellon University; Feminism; Women--education--Pennsylvania--Pittsburgh; Women's issues, global trends; Pennsylvania--Pittsburgh; Barkun, Deborah; Harvey, Anne Marie
Records History
The Carnegie Mellon University Women's Center celebrated its grand opening on January 26, 1990. The development of the Center was a collaborated effort of hundreds of signatures collected in support of a center and a proposal drafted by Deborah Barkun and Anne Marie Harvey in the Spring of 1989. The center grew out of an organization known as the Women's Issues Collective of which Barkun and Harvey were both members.
The Women's Center has a component known as the Women's Center Collective which makes administrative and business decisions. These decisions are made by consensus of each member. The Collective regularly meets through out the academic year. Active participation in the Collective is encouraged after attending two meetings.
The Women's Center works in collaboration with organizations in the surrounding area such as Women's Health Services, Pittsburgh Action Against Rape(PAAR), the Pittsburgh AIDS Task Force (PATF), the Women's Place (Pittsburgh's shelter for battered women).
Scope and Content Note
This collection contains six years of records from The Carnegie Mellon University Women's Center. The collection consists of nine series the majority of which are categorized by subject with the exception of the centers' correspondence records. The majority of the collection is paper with the exception of three photos from a center slumber party. This collection also contains nine file folders of the Center's program announcements (fliers) and several lists of the contents of the Center's Library. For those not familiar with the Women's Center the informational pamphlets that explain the purpose of the center will serve to be helpful for the use of the collection. These can be found under the section pertaining to the Center's Organizational Structure.
An important component of this collection is background information pertaining to The Women's Issue Collective. It was this organization that helped develop the idea of a center.
Provenance
This collection was transferred from the Women's Center to the Carnegie Mellon University Archives in 1994.
Collection List
- Organizational Structure, 1990-91
  - Founding of Women's Issues Collective--20 Items (Folder 1)
  - Informational Pamphlets--8 Items, N.D. (Folder 2)
  - Administrative Papers--Old Notes, 1990-91 (Folder 3)
  - Administrative Papers--Requests, Events, Minutes, 1990-91 (Folder 4)
  - Administrative Papers--Notes, Requests, Event Log, Contacts, CMU Index, 1991 (Folder 5)
  - Administrative Papers--Maintenance Request--2 Items, N.D. (Folder 6)
  - Program Booklet--1 item, 1990-91 (Folder 7)
  - Staff Manual--1 Item, Fall 1990 (Folder 8)
- Correspondence, 1989-91
  - Newsletters--14 Items, 1989-90, 1994, N.D. (Folder 9)
  - Postcards--9 Items, 1991 (Folder 10)
  - Inter-Office--3 Items, February 1991 (Folder 11)
  - E-Mail--2 Items, October 30, 1990 (Folder 12)
- Center Programs, 1990-92
  - Announcements--Pot Luck Dinner, What is the Women's Center?, CMU Lesbian/Bisexual Discussion Group--7 Items, 1991-92, N.D. (Folder 13)
  - Announcements--Stop Rape--Date Rape--8 Items, 1991, N.D. (Folder 14)
  - Monthly Calendar--February, March, April--3 Items (Folder 15)
  - Announcements--Coffeehouse--5 Items, N.D. (Folder 16)
  - Announcements--International Women's Day--5 Items, N.D. (Folder 17)
  - Announcements--Slumber party, Photo--4 Items, N.D. (Folder 18)
  - Announcements--Center Birthday, Dance--3 Items, N.D. (Folder 19)
  - Announcements--Women's Collective Meetings--13 Items, N.D. (Folder 20)
  - Announcements--Movie Night--9 Items, N.D. (Folder 21)
  - Announcements--Sex Week--3 Items, N.D. (Folder 22)
  - Posters, Co- Sponsored Events--4 Items, 1990, N.D. (Folder 23)
- Employment Opportunities, October 1990
  - Volunteer Options, Working Mothers, Women's Yellow Pages--4 Items, October 1990, N.D. (Folder 24)
- Women's Issues, 1988-91, 1994
  - Magazine Clippings, Advertisements--14 Items, 1988, 1990-91, 1994, N.D. (Folder 25)
  - News Clippings--Abortion--31 Items, 1989-91 (Folder 26)
- Library, 1992-93
  - New Book List--1 Item, 1992 (Folder 27)
  - Table of Contents--2 Items, 1992-93 (Folder 28)
  - Table of Contents--1 Item, March 17, 1993 (Folder 29)
  - Updating the Library--1 Item, March 17, 1993 (Folder 30)
  - Subject List--1 Item, N.D. (Folder 31)
  - Donor List--1 Item, N.D. (Folder 32)
  - Lost Book List--4 Items, N.D. (Folder 33)
- Independent Organizations, 1989-91, 1994
  - Program Announcements--Young Women's Speak Out, National Organization for Women, Bisexual/Gay and Lesbian Alliance Society, Center for Violent Crimes, Pittsburgh Pro Choice Escorts, Men Against Rape Pornography, Student Affairs, National Young Feminist, GRRRL Power, Women's Work in Progress--13 Items, 1990-91, 1994 (Folder 34)
  - Program Announcements--Women's Work in Progress--1 Item, N.D. (Folder 35)
  - Publications--Campus Police Street Safety, GRRLS Skankan, We Remember African American Women are for Reproductive Freedom, ACLU Abortion Control Act of 1989, Catholics for a Free Choice, Planned Parenthood, Choice Legal Abortion: Pro Con--10 Items, N.D. (Folder 36)
  - Research Report--Vogue--24 Items, 1989 (Folder 37)
  - Research Reports--Cosmopolitan--6 Item, 1989 (Folder 38)
- Independent Persons
  - Publications--George Grant The Legacy of Planned Parenthood, Kathleen E. Downey/The Serenity Prayer--2 Items, N.D. (Folder 39)